Frank Ormsby papers, circa 1967-2004
Emory University
Frank Ormsby papers, circa 1967-2004
Ormsby, Frank, 1947-
Manuscript Collection No. 805
22.5 linear ft. (40 boxes) and 20 oversized papers (OP)
Personal and literary papers of Irish poet Frank Ormsby.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Purchase, 1997, with subsequent additions.
Restrictions on access
Special restrictions apply: Subseries 1.1, letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers.
Collection stored off-site. Researchers must contact MARBL in advance to access this collection.
Biographical Note
A central figure in Ulster's literary culture since the late 1960's, Frank Ormsby has led a lively and multifarious writing life as a poet, book and magazine editor, and teacher based in Belfast. Born in Enniskillen, County Fermanagh, Northern Ireland in 1947, Ormsby studied English at Queen's University Belfast, where he received an MA. In 1971, he began teaching at the Royal Belfast Academical Institution, and he has been Head of English there for many years.
As a poet, Ormsby established himself in the early seventies with two chapbooks, Ripe for Company (1971) and Business as Usual (1973). During the 1971-1972 academic year, Ormsby also participated in the Belfast Group meetings organized by Seamus Heaney and Michael Allen. He won the Eric Gregory Award in 1974, and his 1977 volume of poems, A Store of Candles, was a Poetry Book Society Choice. Ormsby's other collections of poems, A Northern Spring (1986) and The Ghost Train (1995) have been published with the Gallery Press. In 1992, Ormsby won a Cultural Traditions Award given in memory of John Hewitt, and in 2002 he was honored with the Lawrence O'Shaughnessy Award for Poetry from the University of St Thomas at St Paul, Minnesota.
Ormsby began his editorial career in 1969, when he and Michael Foley succeeded James Simmons as co-editors of The Honest Ulsterman. From 1972 to 1984, Ormsby was the sole editor of this small but important literary magazine that offered both younger and established Northern Irish writers invaluable access to a wider public. After editing The Honest Ulsterman with Robert Johnstone from 1984 until 1989, Ormsby left to dedicate himself both to his own poetry and various other editorial projects.
Ormsby's other editorial projects including several very important anthologies produced since the late 1970's. Poets From Northern Ireland was first published in 1979 and then revised in 1990. Similarly, The Long Embrace: Twentieth Century Irish Love Poems was published in 1987 and also reprinted in 1990. In 1987, Ormsby produced Northern Windows: An Anthology of Ulster Autobiography. Another anthology of mostly prose, Thine in Storm and Calm: An Amanda McKittrick Ros Reader, was released in 1988. Published in 1991, The Collected Poems of John Hewitt is a definitive and extensively annotated collection of this major Belfast poet's work. Ormsby's A Rage for Order: Poetry of the Northern Ireland Troubles (1992) is a much heralded and widely used anthology of "Troubles poetry." His most recent anthology is The Hip Flask: Short Poems from Ireland (2001). In addition to these individual volumes, he edited the Poetry Ireland Review (Numbers 53-56).
Scope and Content Note
The Frank Ormsby papers consist of the poet-editor's personal and literary papers from 1968 to 2004. These papers catalog Ormsby's literary career as a poet, an anthologist, and a long-term editor of The Honest Ulsterman. The collection focuses on two interconnected areas of Ormsby's literary life. On one hand, the papers highlight Ormsby's output as a poet, a writer about poetry, and an editor-anthologist. On the other hand, this collection is notable for its materials relating to The Honest Ulsterman and Ormsby's role as editor of this magazine, which played an important role in the late twentieth century literary culture of Northern Ireland.
Ormsby's poetry has been consistently well-received and widely acknowledged since the early 1970's. An extensive series of manuscript and typescript drafts of published and unpublished poems charts the development of the poet across time. Like many other poets in Ireland and Great Britain, Ormsby has also enjoyed a parallel career as a literary journalist. He has written many reviews and essays about other writers and collections of poetry.
Apart from his writing poetry and critical prose and his magazine editing, Ormsby, as anthologist and literary editor, has produced seven anthologies or other edited volumes. Materials relating to the publication of these volumes are arranged in a distinct subseries of writing by Ormsby. Such materials include: bibliographical and biographical research materials, permissions, contents lists and indexes, drafts of introductions, and copies of primary documents. Correspondence with contributors, editors, or publishers is kept separately in the subseries for personal literary correspondence. Similarly, reviews and other printed matter relating to these texts are found in the subseries for printed material about Ormsby.
His editorial work on these volumes as well as with The Honest Ulsterman has ensured a wide and varied correspondence with many important writers in Ireland and Great Britain. Though Ormsby's personal literary correspondence and his editorial correspondence relating to The Honest Ulsterman are located in two distinct series, individual letters frequently mention both the poet's own work and The Honest Ulsterman. Information related to the poet and to the magazine may be found throughout the collection. In this collection's several correspondence subseries, writers of interest include Ciaran Carson, Peter Fallon, Seamus Heaney, John Hewitt, Kathleen Jamie, Edna and Michael Longley, Derek Mahon, Medbh McGuckian, Paul Muldoon, Tom Paulin, Carol Rumens, and James Simmons, among many others.
Because of the magazine's importance, both for Ormsby and Northern Irish literary culture, The Honest Ulsterman materials constitute a separate and sizeable series, which includes correspondence, author files, manuscript submissions, publications, and printed material regarding The Honest Ulsterman. Manuscript and typescript drafts of poetry and prose sent to Ormsby are divided according to those submitted for magazine publication and those shared with the poet on a more personal basis. Because friends sent material both for personal reasons and for publication, the series of writings by others is relatively small compared to The Honest Ulsterman author files and magazine submissions subseries. Anything sent with an eye towards publication has been kept in The Honest Ulsterman series. Similarly, printed material regarding the magazine is arranged separately from other printed material relating to Ormsby and his work as poet and anthologist.
Other important materials include worksheets by Norman Dugdale, Seamus Heaney, Michael Longley, Paul Muldoon, Bernard MacLaverty, and James Simmons from meetings of the Belfast Group in 1971-1972. Photographs of many of the personages whose work is represented in this collection are arranged in a separate series.
Unprocessed additions include writings by Ormsby, writings by others including Michael Longley and James Simmons, correspondence, and printed material.
Arrangement Note
Organized into eight series: (1) Correspondence, (2) The Honest Ulsterman literary materials, (3) Writings by Ormsby, (4) Writing by others, (5) Printed material by and about Ormsby, (6) Photographs, (7) Personal materials, and (8) Unprocessed additions.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Carson, Ciaran, 1948-; Fallon, Peter, 1951-; Heaney, Seamus, 1939-; Hewitt, John Harold, 1907-; Jamie, Kathleen, 1962-; Longley, Edna.; Longley, Michael, 1939-; Mahon, Derek, 1941-; McGuckian, Medbh, 1950-; Muldoon, Paul.; Paulin, Tom.; Rumens, Carol.; Simmons, James, 1933-
Uniform Titles
Honest ulsterman.
Topical Terms
English poetry--Irish authors--20th century.; Irish poetry--20th century.; Poets, Irish--20th century.; Publishers and publishing--Ireland.
Form/Genre Terms
Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Poems.
Occupation
Editor.; Poet.
Related Materials in This Repository
Seamus Heaney collection,, Michael Longley papers, Derek Mahon papers, Medbh McGuckian papers, Tom Paulin papers, Peter Fallon/Gallery Press papers.
Description of Series
- Correspondence, 1969-1997, Series 1; Boxes 1-4
  Scope and Content Note
  The correspondence series is comprised of two subseries, one for personal literary correspondence and the other for project and business correspondence. Personal literary correspondence refers to letters for the most part sent to Ormsby regarding his own literary career as a poet or educator. The project and business correspondence subseries contains communications of a contractual and/or editorial nature sent to Ormsby by the editors or publishing houses that produced his volumes of poetry and other books.
  One of the curious features of the correspondence in the Frank Ormsby papers is that it is both personal and editorial. Often in the same letter, a correspondent will address Ormsby as editor of The Honest Ulsterman and then comment on Ormsby's own poetry or editorial projects. Even as correspondence related to Ormsby's careers as poet and magazine editor is often interrelated, an effort has been made to distinguish and arrange separately letters pertaining to each of these roles. Correspondence relating to The Honest Ulsterman will be found in two places in Series 2. Some letters are located in author files and others are in a correspondence subseries. Notable writers in this series include: Peter Fallon, Seamus Heaney, John Hewitt, Edna and Michael Longley, Tom Paulin, and James Simmons.
  Restrictions on access
  Special restrictions apply: Subseries 1.1, letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers.
  Arrangement Note
  Organized into two subseries: (1.1) Personal literary correspondence and (1.2) Project and business correspondence.
  - Personal literary correspondence, 1969-1997, Subseries 1.1; Box 1 - Box 2: folders 1-6
    The personal literary correspondence showcases Frank Ormsby's wide-ranging literary interests and activities. Much of this correspondence is of both a personal and a professional nature. Of special interest is correspondence with various newspaper, magazine, and journal editors about the publication of Ormsby's own poetry and prose. This subseries also contains correspondence with various colleagues and academics about poetry or history as well as Ormsby's own activities and travel plans. The final folder contains drafts of letters that Ormsby has sent to others. Personal correspondence with Seamus Heaney, which is restricted, is located at the end of this correspondence series.
    Arranged in chronologic order, with undated correspondence is filed at the end of the subseries.
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Undated correspondence (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Undated correspondence (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1994-1996 correspondence from Ormsby (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Restricted Correspondence
    - Heaney, Seamus, 1971-1996 (13 items) (Box 2a, Folder 1)
    - Heaney, Seamus, 1975-1996, announcements and invitations (Box 2a, Folder 2)
  - Project and business correspondence, 1969-1996, Subseries 1.2; Box 2: folders 7-15 - Box 4
    This subseries contains Ormsby's correspondence of an editorial and/or business nature. The subseries is divided into two subsections. The project correspondence subsection attempts to maintain the integrity of Ormsby's own files arranged according to specific book projects that he edited. Most of the correspondence in these folders pertains to project research, permissions, and contributors' correspondence. Specific contractual or financial correspondence related to the various book projects is included with the correspondence organized according to publisher.
    The business correspondence subsection is arranged according to specific publishing houses. Individual items are then arranged chronologically. In some cases, as in the Gallery Press or Oxford University Press correspondence, extensive editorial exchanges between the publisher and Ormsby (as poet) are segregated from the contractual and fiduciary correspondence. In other instances, as in the Blackstaff Press correspondence, contractual and editorial correspondence is thoroughly mixed together. In many cases, editors simultaneously refer to or attach together both editorial comments and contractual materials related to the books Ormsby edited.
    - Project Correspondence
    - Poets from the North of Ireland, project correspondence, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Poets from the North of Ireland, project correspondence, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Thine in Storm and Calm: An Amanda McKittrick Ros Reader, project correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - The Long Embrace: Twentieth Century Irish Love Poems, project correspondence, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Collected Poems of John Hewitt, project correspondence, 1988-1996 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - A Rage for Order, project correspondence, 1992 and undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Business Correspondence
    - BBC, contractual and editorial correspondence, 1969-1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - BBC, contractual and editorial correspondence, 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - BBC, contractual and editorial correspondence, 1988-1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Belfast Telegraph, contracts and royalty statements, 1978-1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Blackstaff Press, contractual and editorial correspondence, 1976-1986 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Blackstaff Press, contractual and editorial correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Blackstaff Press, contractual and editorial correspondence, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Blackstaff Press, contractual and editorial correspondence, 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Faber and Faber, contractual and editorial correspondence, 1978, 1990, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Faber and Faber, contractual and editorial correspondence, 1989 [re: reissue of The Long Embrace: Twentieth Century Irish Love Poems] (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Gallery Press, editorial correspondence, 1985-1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Gallery Press, editorial correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Gallery Press, editorial correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Gallery Press, contracts and royalty statements, 1986-1995 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Irish Press, royalty statements, 1970-1978 [from David Marcus materials] (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Oxford University Press, editorial correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Oxford University Press, editorial correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Oxford University Press, editorial correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Oxford University Press, editorial correspondence, 1982-1993 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Oxford University Press, editorial correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Oxford University Press, contracts and Royalty statements, 1977-1986 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Radio Telefis Eireann, contracts and royalty statements, 1973-1990 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Regency Press, correspondence, 1969-1984 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Secker & Warburg, contractual and editorial correspondence, 1984-1989 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Secker & Warburg, correspondence [includes: A Northern Spring broadcast running order] (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Secker & Warburg, correspondence [includes: "County Fermanagh," photocopy of chapter from 32 Counties (1989) by Frank Ormsby] (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Secker & Warburg, correspondence [includes: miscellaneous publishers' addresses] (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Ulster Museum, contracts and royalty statements, 1990-1996 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous contracts and royalty statements (Box 4, Folder 21)
- The Honest Ulsterman literary materials, 1967-1990, Series 2; Boxes 5-16; OP 1 - 5
  The volume and significance of the Ormsby collection's papers related to The Honest Ulsterman necessitate the organization of this material in a distinct series. This series contains documents pertaining to all aspects of the magazine's production.
  As mentioned, the correspondence received by Ormsby from readers and contributors to The Honest Ulsterman is distinguished from Ormsby's other personal literary and business correspondence. It is important to note that many of the letters referring to The Honest Ulsterman in the present series also mention Ormsby's personal or individual poetic life. An effort has been made to distinguish between letters that focus principally on the personal or poetic life and those chiefly addressed to Ormsby's role as a magazine editor. But, if researching The Honest Ulsterman, it is advisable to examine all the correspondence in the Ormsby collection. Note also that additional correspondence from specific individuals is contained in the author files subseries. All correspondence in either the author files or The Honest Ulsterman correspondence subseries is arranged chronologically. The restricted Seamus Heaney correspondence (1971-1996) is kept with personal literary correspondence (Subseries 1.1) because individual letters make mention not only of Honest Ulsterman submissions but Ormsby's other editorial and poetic projects.
  The author files reflect Ormsby's own organizational system in which the editor maintained specific files of selected contributors to The Honest Ulsterman. In addition to correspondence, these files include an individual author's publication submissions of poetry and prose, as well as promotional and other printed material by and about the writer in question.
  Another subseries includes work submitted to The Honest Ulsterman by authors not included in Ormsby's original author files. Unlike individual works that are catalogued by title in the author files, these poetry and prose submissions are collected by author. The titles of these submissions are not discretely listed. Two other subseries include materials related to the actual publication of specific volumes of The Honest Ulsterman and assorted printed material about the magazine.
  Organized into five subseries: (2.1) The Honest Ulsterman correspondence (2.2) The Honest Ulsterman author files (2.3) Submissions to The Honest Ulsterman (2.4) Ulsterman Publications and (2.5) Printed material about The Honest Ulsterman.
  - The Honest Ulsterman correspondence, 1967-1990, Subseries 2.1; Boxes 5-6
    All correspondence pertains to some aspect of Ormsby's involvement with The Honest Ulsterman. Many of the pieces are cover letters submitted with various poems or prose documents, though another large number of letters also deals with subscriptions to magazine. The earliest correspondence from 1967 to 1969 includes letters both to and from James Simmons, the founder and first editor of The Honest Ulsterman. Ormsby joined the operation as an editor in 1969.
    Correspondence is arranged in chronological order. Undated correspondence is collected at the end of the subseries along with copies or drafts of letters sent by Ormsby.
    - 1967 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1968 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1971 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1972 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1973 January - June (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1973 July - December (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - 1974 January - February (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 1974 March - April (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - 1974 May - June (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - 1974 July - August (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - 1974 September - October (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - 1974 November - December (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - 1975 January - February (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - 1975 March - April (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - 1975 May - June (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - 1975 July - August (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - 1975 September - October (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - 1975 November - December (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - 1976 January - February (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - 1976 March - April (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - 1976 May - June (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - 1976 July - August (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - 1976 September - October (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - 1976 November - December (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - 1977 January - February (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - 1977 March - April (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - 1977 May - June (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - 1977 July - August (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - 1977 September - October (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - 1977 November - December (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - 1978 January - February (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - 1978 March - April (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - 1978 May - June (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - 1978 July - August (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - 1978 September - October (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - 1978 November - December (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - 1979 January - February (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 1979 March - April (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 1979 May - June (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 1979 July - August (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - 1979 September - October (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - 1979 November - December (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 1980 January - February (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 1980 March - April (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - 1980 May - June (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - 1980 July - August (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - 1980 September - October (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - 1980 November - December (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - 1981 January - February (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - 1981 March - April (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - 1981 May - June (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - 1981 July - August (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - 1981 September - October (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - 1981 November - December (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - 1982 January - March (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - 1982 April - June (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - 1982 July - September (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - 1982 October - December (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - 1983 January - March (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - 1983 April - June (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - 1983 July - September (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - 1983 October - December (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - 1984 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - 1985 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - 1986 - 1990 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Undated correspondence No. 1 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Undated correspondence No. 2 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - 1972-1975, The Honest Ulsterman correspondence from Ormsby (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - The Honest Ulsterman author files, 1968-1996, Subseries 2.2; Boxes 7-12; OP1-3